I just met you on a bus,
التقيت بك للتو على متن حافلة
and we would really like to get to know each other,
وكان كلانا يتوق لمعرفة الآخر
but I've got to get off at the next stop,
إلا أنني كنت مضطرة للنزول في المحطة التالية
so you're going to tell me three things about yourself
وبذلك ستقول لي 3 أشياء عنك
that just define you as a person,
تصف شخصيتك
that will help me understand who you are,
تساعدني لأن أفهم من أنت
three things that just get to your very essence.
ثلاثة أشياء تلخص كينونتك
And what I'm wondering
وما أود معرفته
is, of those three things,
من هذه الأشياء الثلاثة
is any one of them
هل كان أحدها يتمثل
surviving some kind of trauma?
الشفاء من صدمة ما؟
Cancer survivor, rape survivor,
الشفاء من السرطان أو الاغتصاب
Holocaust survivor, incest survivor.
أو محرقة أو سفاح القربى
Ever notice how we tend to identify ourselves
هل سبق أن لاحظتم كيف ننزع لتحديد ملامحنا
by our wounds?
بجروحنا؟
And where I have seen this survivor identity
وقد لاحظت أن حالات النجاة
have the most consequences
ذات العواقب الأشد
is in the cancer community.
توجد في شريحة المصابين بالسرطان
And I've been around this community for a long time,
وقد قضيت وقتاً طويلاً مع هذه الشريحة
because I've been a hospice and a hospital chaplain
فقد عملت ممرضة في ملحق في إحدى المشافي
for almost 30 years.
لمدة 30 عاماً
And in 2005, I was working at a big cancer center
وفي 2005، كنت أعمل في مركز كبير للسرطان
when I received the news that
عندما تلقيت أخباراً مفادها
my mother had breast cancer.
أن والدتي مصابة بسرطان الثدي
And then five days later,
بعد 5 أيام
I received the news that I had breast cancer.
تلقيت خبراً أنني مصابة بسرطان الثدي
My mother and I can be competitive —
كثيراً ما كنت أتنافس مع أمي —
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)
but I was really not trying to compete with her on this one.
لكنني ما كنت لأتنافس معها في ذلك المرض
And in fact, I thought, well,
وكنت أقول في قرارة نفسي
if you have to have cancer,
إذا كانت الإصابة بالسرطان حتمية
it's pretty convenient to be working
فمن الجيد العمل
at a place that treats it.
في مكان مخصص لمعالجته
But this is what I heard from a lot of outraged people.
لكن هذا ما سمعته من الكثير من الأشخاص الغاضبين
What?
ماذا؟
You're the chaplain.
أنت قسيسة
You should be immune.
يجب أن تكوني منيعة
Like, maybe I should have just gotten off
ربما وجب علي أن أتلقى
with a warning instead of an actual ticket,
تحذيراً عوضاً عن التذكرة الفعلية
because I'm on the force.
فأنا في موقع القوة
So I did get my treatment at the cancer center where I worked,
تلقيت علاجي في مركز السرطان حيث كنت أعمل
which was amazingly convenient,
من حسن الحظ
and I had chemotherapy
تلقيت علاجاً كيماوياً
and a mastectomy, and a saline implant put in,
وتم استئصال الثدي ووضع زرعة ملحية
and so before I say another word, let me just say right now,
وقبل أن أتابع حديثي دعوني أكتفي الآن بالقول
this is the fake one. (Laughter)
أن الثدي الاصطناعي هنا
I have found that I need to get that out of the way,
أجد نفسي مضطرة لتوضيح ذلك
because I'll see somebody go
فقد يهمس أحدهم بالقول:
"Oh, I know it's this one."
"حسناً أعلم إنه هنا"
And then I'll move or I'll gesture and they'll go,
ومن ثم عندما أتحرك أو أؤمئ قد يقول:
"No, it's that one."
"لا، بل ذاك الثدي"
So now you know.
ها أنتم تعلمون الآن
I learned a lot being a patient,
تعلمت الكثير أثناء المرض
and one of the surprising things was
وإحدى الأشياء المذهلة
that only a small part of the cancer experience
أن جزءاً صغيراً من علاج السرطان
is about medicine.
يتمثل بالدواء
Most of it is about feelings and faith
لكن الجزء الأكبر يتمثل بالمشاعر والإيمان
and losing and finding your identity
وأن تفقد هويتك وتجدها من جديد
and discovering strength
وأن تكتشف القوة
and flexibility you never even knew you had.
والمرونة التي لم تعرف يوماً أنك تمتلكها
It's about realizing that
الأمر يتعلق بإدراك
the most important things in life are
أن الأشياء الأكثر أهمية في الحياة
not things at all, but relationships,
ليست الأشياء بتاتاً، بل العلاقات
and it's about laughing in the face of uncertainty
يتعلق الأمر بمواجهة المجهول بضحكة
and learning that the way to get out of almost anything
وإدراك أن طريقة الخروج من أي مأزق
is to say, "I have cancer."
هي بالقول: "لدي سرطان"
So the other thing I learned was that
تعلمت أيضاً
I don't have to take on "cancer survivor"
أنني لست مضطرة لاتخاذ "ناجية من السرطان"
as my identity,
هوية لي
but, boy, are there powerful forces
لكن ثمة قوى خارقة
pushing me to do just that.
تدفعني لفعل ذلك
Now, don't, please, misunderstand me.
لا تسيؤوا فهمي رجاء
Cancer organizations
منظمات السرطان
and the drive for early screening
والحملة التي تدعو للكشف المبكر
and cancer awareness and cancer research
والتوعية والأبحاث المتمحورة حول السرطان
have normalized cancer,
كلها عملت على تطبيع السرطان
and this is a wonderful thing.
وهذا شيء رائع
We can now talk about cancer
يمكننا التحدث الآن عن السرطان
without whispering.
دون همس
We can talk about cancer and we can support one another.
نستطيع التحدث عن السرطان وندعم بعضنا
But sometimes, it feels
لكن أحياناً يبدو
like people go a little overboard
وكأن الناس تبالغ قليلاً
and they start telling us how we're going to feel.
وتبدأ بإخبارنا كيف سنشعر
So about a week after my surgery,
بعد أسبوع من العمل الجراحي
we had a houseguest.
جاءنا زائر
That was probably our first mistake.
وكانت تلك أولى أخطائنا
And keep in mind that
وتذكروا
at this point in my life
في ذلك الوقت
I had been a chaplain for over 20 years,
كنت أعمل ممرضة لأكثر من 20 عاماً
and issues like dying and death
وجميع القضايا إزاء الموت
and the meaning of life,
ومعنى الحياة
these are all things I'd been yakking about forever.
كلها أشياء لطالما كنت أثرثر حولها
So at dinner that night,
أثناء العشاء في تلك الليلة
our houseguest proceeds to stretch his arms up over his head,
وضع الزائر ذراعيه فوق رأسه
and say, "You know, Deb,
وقال: "أتعلمين يا (ديب)
now you're really going to learn what's important.
ستدركين الآن ما هو مهم بالنسبة لك
Yes, you are going to make some big changes
ستقومين بإحداث بعض التغييرات الكبيرة
in your life,
في حياتك
and now you're going to start thinking about your death.
وستبدأين بالتفكير بالموت
Yep, this cancer is your wakeup call."
أجل، السرطان هو نداء اليقظة"
Now, these are golden words
هذه الكلمات ذات أهمية كبيرة
coming from someone who is speaking about
تأتي على لسان شخص يتحدث عن
their own experience,
تجربته الشخصية
but when someone is telling you
لكن عندما يخبرك أحدهم
how you are going to feel,
كيف ستشعر فيما بعد
it's instant crap.
فهذه الحماقة بعينها
The only reason I did not kill him
امتنعت عن قتله
with my bare hands
بيدي العاريتين
was because I could not lift my right arm.
لأنني لم أستطع رفع يدي اليمنى
But I did say a really bad word to him,
لكنني قذفته بعبارات مشينة
followed by a regular word, that —
متبوعة بعبارات اعتيادية —
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)
made my husband say, "She's on narcotics."
جعلت زوجي يقول: "إنها تحت تأثير المخدر"
And then after my treatment, it just felt like
وبعد تلقي العلاج، شعرت
everyone was telling me what my experience was going to mean.
بأن كل شخص يحاول إيجاد معنى لتجربتي
"Oh, this means you're going to be doing the walk."
"هذا يعني أنك ستتمشين وتتنزهين"
"Oh, this means you're coming to the luncheon."
"هذا يعني أنك مدعوة لطعام الغداء"
"This means you're going to be wearing
"هذا يعني أن عليك ارتداء
the pink ribbon and the pink t-shirt
الشريط الوردي والقميص الزهري
and the headband and the earrings
وعصبة الرأس والأقراط
and the bracelet and the panties."
والسوار والسراويل."
Panties. No, seriously, google it.
سراويل. ليست مزحة، ابحثو في غووغل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
How is that raising awareness?
كيف يزيد ذلك من الوعي؟!
Only my husband should be seeing my panties.
لا يجب أن يرى أحد سراويلي سوى زوجي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He's pretty aware of cancer already.
فهو مدرك أصلاً بوجود السرطان
It was at that point where I felt like, oh my God,
شعرت عند ذلك الحد
this is just taking over my life.
أن ذلك يسيطر على حياتي
And that's when I told myself, claim your experience.
وحينها قلت لنفسي: امتلك تجربتك
Don't let it claim you.
ولا تدعيها تتملكك
We all know that
نعلم جميعاً
the way to cope with trauma, with loss,
أن طريقة التكيف مع المرض أو الفقدان
with any life-changing experience,
أو التجارب التي تحدث تغيراً جذرياً
is to find meaning.
هي بإيجاد المعنى
But here's the thing:
لكن الأمر كالتالي:
No one can tell us
لا أحد يستطيع إخبارنا
what our experience means.
معنى تجربتنا
We have to decide what it means.
يجب أن نحدد المعنى بأنفسنا
And it doesn't have to be some gigantic,
وليس بالضرورة أن يكون المعنى
extroverted meaning.
ضخم وكبير
We don't all have to start a foundation
ليس جميعنا مضطر لإنشاء مؤسسة
or an organization or write a book
أو منظمة أو تأليف كتاب
or make a documentary.
أو صناعة فيلم وثائقي
Meaning can be quiet
قد يكون المعنى هادئاً
and introverted.
وداخلياً
Maybe we make one small decision about our lives
ربما قرار واحد صغير في حياتنا
that can bring about big change.
يمكن أن يؤدي إلى تغيير كبير
Many years ago, I had a patient,
منذ عدة سنوات، التقيت بمريض
just a wonderful young man
شاب رائع
who was loved by the staff,
أحبه الطاقم الطبي
and so it was something of a shock to us to realize
وكانت صدمة لنا عندما علمنا
that he had no friends.
أنه لا يملك أصدقاء
He lived by himself,
يعيش بمفرده
he would come in for chemotherapy by himself,
يأتي إلى العلاج الكيماوي بمفرده
he would receive his treatment,
يتلقى علاجه
and then he'd walk home alone.
ويعود إلى منزله وحيداً
And I even asked him. I said, "Hey,
وقد طرحت عليه سؤالاً:
how come you never bring a friend with you?"
"لماذا لا تأتي بصحبة أحد أصدقائك؟"
And he said, "I don't really have any friends."
فأجاب: "ليس لدي من أصدقاء"
But he had tons of friends on the infusion floor.
لكنه كسب عشرات الأصدقاء في طابق الغرس
We all loved him, and people were going in and out of his room all the time.
أحببناه جميعاً وكانت الناس تتوافد إلى غرفته وتخرج منها
So at his last chemo,
وعند جلسة الكيماوي الأخيرة
we sang him the song
أنشدنا له أغنية
and we put the crown on his head and we blew the bubbles,
ووضعنا التاج على رأسه ونفخنا الفقاعات
and then I asked him, I said,
ثم سألته:
"So what are you going to do now?"
"ما الذي ستفعله الآن؟"
And he answered,
فأجاب
"Make friends."
"تكوين الصداقات"
And he did.
وقد فعل ذلك
He started volunteering and he made friends there,
بدأ بالتطوع وكسب الأصدقاء هناك
and he began going to a church
وبدأ بالذهاب للكنيسة وكسب الأصدقاء هناك
and at Christmas he invited my husband and me to a party in his apartment,
وفي الكريسماس وجه دعوة لي ولزوجي لحضور حفلة في شقته
and the place was filled with his friends.
وقد امتلأ المكان بأصدقائه
Claim your experience.
سيطر على تجربتك
Don't let it claim you.
لا تدعها تسيطر عليك
He decided that the meaning of his experience
لقد قرر أن معنى تجربته
was to know the joy of friendship,
ان يدرك بهجة تكوين صداقات
and then learn to make friends.
وبناء عليه، تعلم تكوين الصداقات
So what about you?
ماذا عنكم؟
How are you going to find meaning
كيف ستجدون المعنى
in your crappy experience?
في تجربتكم المزرية؟
It could be a recent one,
قد تكون تجربة حديثة
or it could be one that you've been carrying around
أو تجربة تحملونها في ذاكرتكم
for a really long time.
منذ وقت طويل
It's never too late to change what it means,
لم يفت الأوان لتغيير المعنى
because meaning is dynamic.
لأن المعنى ديناميكي
What it means today
المعنى اليوم
may not be what it means a year from now,
قد لا يبقى نفسه بعد سنة
or 10 years from now.
أو بعد 10 سنوات
It's never too late to become someone other
لم يفت الأوان لتصبح شخصاً آخر
than simply a survivor.
بدلاً من مجرد ناجٍ
Hear how static that word sounds?
أتسمعون كم هي هامدة هذه المفردة؟
Survivor.
ناجٍ
No movement, no growth.
لا حركة، لا نمو
Claim your experience.
امتلك تجربتك
Don't let it claim you, because if you do,
لا تدعها تتملكك، وإلا
I believe you will become trapped,
فستكون في مأزق
you will not grow, you will not evolve.
ولن تنضج ولن تتطور
But of course, sometimes it's not outside pressures
بالطبع أحياناً ليست الضغوط الخارجية
that cause us to take on that identity of survivor.
التي تدفعنا لتبني الهوية الناجية
Sometimes we just like the perks.
أحياناً نحب رفع المعنويات
Sometimes there's a payoff.
أحياناً يكون هناك مكافأة
But then we get stuck.
لكننا سنقع في مأزق
Now, one of the first things I learned
إحدى الأشياء التي تعلمتها
as a chaplain intern was the three C's
كممرضة هي ثلاثة أشياء
of the chaplain's job:
من عملي كممرضة:
Comfort, clarify and, when necessary, confront
الراحة والتوضيح والمواجهة عند الحاجة
or challenge.
أو التحدي
Now, we all pretty much love the comforting
وجميعنا نحب الراحة
and the clarifying.
والتوضيح
The confronting, not so much.
ولا نحبذ المواجهة كثيراً
One of the other things that I loved
إحدى الأشياء التي أحببتها
about being a chaplain was
في وظيفتي كممرضة
seeing patients a year, or even several years
رؤية المرضى بعد سنة أو عدة سنوات
after their treatment, because
بعد تلقيهم العلاج
it was just really cool to see how they had changed
فكم كان رائعاً رؤية مدى التغير الذي طرأ على حياتهم
and how their lives had evolved
وكم تطورت حياتهم
and what had happened to them.
وماذا حدث لهم
So I was thrilled one day
ذات يوم انتابتني الغبطة
to get a page down into the lobby of the clinic
عندما تلقيت استدعاء لقاعة الاستقبال بالمستشفي
from a patient who I had seen the year before,
من مريضة لم أرها منذ سنة
and she was there with her two adult daughters,
كانت برفقة ابنتيها
who I also knew, for her one year follow-up exam.
اللتين كنت أعرفهما، لإجراء الفحص السنوي
So I got down to the lobby, and they were ecstatic
ذهبت إلى قاعة الاستقبال وكنّ مسرورات
because she had just gotten all of her test results back
لأنها تلقت جميع نتائج الفحوص
and she was NED: No Evidence of Disease.
وكانت خالية من أي عرض
Which I used to think meant Not Entirely Dead.
وهذا يعني بالنسبة لي أنها ليست ميتة كلياً
So they were ecstatic, we sat down to visit,
لذا انتابهن شعور بالسعادة وقمنا بزيارتهن
and it was so weird, because
وكان الأمر غريباً
within two minutes, she started retelling me the story
فخلال دقيقتين، بدأت تقص علي قصتها مجدداً
of her diagnosis and her surgery and her chemo,
عن الأعراض والعملية الجراحية والعلاج الكيماوي
even though, as her chaplain, I saw her every week,
بالرغم من أنني كنت أراها أسبوعياً في المستشفي
and so I knew this story.
فأنا على علم مسبق بقصتها
And she was using words like suffering,
وكانت تستخدم عبارات مثل عذاب
agony, struggle.
وألم مبرح ومعاناة
And she ended her story with,
وأنهت قصتها بعبارة:
"I felt crucified."
"شعرت أنني مصلوبة"
And at that point, her two daughters got up and said,
وعند ذلك الحد توقف ابنتاها وقالتا:
"We're going to go get coffee."
"سنذهب لإحضار القهوة"
And they left.
وغادرتا
Tell me three things about yourself before the next stop.
قل لي ثلاثة أشياء عنك قبل الوصول إلى المحطة التالية
People were leaving the bus before she even got
كانت الناس تغادر الحافلة قبل أن تصل
to number two or number three.
إلى الرقم اثنين أو ثلاثة
So I handed her a tissue,
لذا أعطيتها منديلاً
and I gave her a hug,
وقمت باحتضانها
and then, because I really cared for this woman,
ولأنني أكترث حقاً لأمر هذه المرأة
I said,
قلت
"Get down off your cross."
"ترجّلي عن الصليب"
And she said, "What?"
فقالت: "ماذا؟"
And I repeated, "Get down off your cross."
فكررت جملتي: "ترجّلي من على الصليب"
And to her credit, she could talk about her reasons
وللعلم أنها أبدت أسبابها
for embracing and then clinging to this identity.
لتلقف هويتها والتعلق بها
It got her a lot of attention.
لقد أعطتها الكثير من الانتباه
People were taking care of her for a change.
كان الناس يعتنون بها على سبيل التغيير
But now, it was having the opposite effect.
والآن جائت النتائج عكسية
It was pushing people away.
كانت تدفع الناس بعيداً عنها
People kept leaving to get coffee.
واصل الناس المغادرة لاحتساء القهوة
She felt crucified by her experience,
شعرت بالعذاب من تجربتها
but she didn't want to let that crucified self die.
لكنها لم تود ترك حالة الاقتصاص من الذات
Now, perhaps you are thinking
ربما تعتقدون
I was a little harsh with her,
أنني قسوت عليها
so I must tell you that
لذلك يجب أن أخبركم
I was speaking out of my own experience.
أنني كنت أتحدث عن تجربتي الخاصة
Many, many years before,
منذ زمن طويل
I had been fired from a job that I loved,
تمت إقالتي من وظيفة أحببتها
and I would not stop talking about my innocence
ولم أكن أكف عن التحدث عن برائتي
and the injustice and the betrayal and the deceipt,
وعن عدم المساواة والخيانة والتضليل
until finally, just like this woman,
إلى أن قام الناس كتلك المرأة
people were walking away from me,
بالابتعاد عني
until I finally realized
حتى أدركت أخيراً
I wasn't just processing my feelings,
أنني لست أعبر عن مشاعري وحسب
I was feeding them.
بل أقوم بتغذيتهم
I didn't want to let that crucified self die.
لم أود ترك حالة الاقتصاص من الذات تلك
But we all know that with any resurrection story,
لكننا نعلم جميعاً من قصص الشفاء
you have to die first.
عليك أن تختبر الموت أولاً
The Christian story,
القصة المسيحية
Jesus was dead a whole day in the tomb
كان يسوع المسيح ميتاً في قبر ليوم كامل
before he was resurrected.
لكنه انبعث من جديد
And I believe that for us,
وأعتقد أنه بالنسبة لنا
being in the tomb
كوننا في قبر
means doing our own deep inner work
يعني أننا نقوم بعملنا العميق
around our wounds
حول جروحنا
and allowing ourselves to be healed.
ونسمح لأنفسنا بالتعافي
We have to let that crucified self die
علينا أن نتحرر من حالة الاقتصاص من الذات
so that a new self, a truer self,
وبذلك نفس جديدة أكثر واقعية
is born.
تولد من جديد
We have to let that old story go
يجب أن نتحرر من القصص القديمة
so that a new story, a truer story,
بحيث يمكن لقصة جديدة أكثر واقعية
can be told.
أن تُحكى
Claim your experience. Don't let it claim you.
امتلك تجربتك ولا تدعها تتملكك
What if there were no survivors,
ماذا إن لم يكن من ناجٍ
meaning, what if people decided
ماذا إذا قرر الناس
to just claim their trauma as an experience
أن يتخذوا من صدمتهم تجربة
instead of taking it on as an identity?
بدلاً من اتخاذها كهوية؟
Maybe it would be the end of being
ربما تكون نهاية كونها
trapped in our wounds
محتجزة في جروحنا
and the beginning of amazing
وبداية روعة
self-exploration and discovery and growth.
اكتشاف النفس والنضج
Maybe it would be the start of defining ourselves
ربما تكون بداية تعريف أنفسنا
by who we have become
بما أصبحنا عليه
and who we are becoming.
وما نصبح عليه
So perhaps survivor was not
ربما الناجي لم يكن
one of the three things that you would tell me.
أحد الأشياء الثلاثة التي تقولها لي
No matter.
لا يهم
I just want you all to know that
أردتكم جميعاً أن تعلموا
I am really glad that we are on this bus together,
أنني ممتنة لكوننا على متن هذه الحافلة معاً
and this is my stop.
وهنا محطتي الأخيرة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)